Kim A. Dill-McFarland, PhD

Senior Bioinformatician Division of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, University of Washington 1-206-595-1828; kdillmcfarland@gmail.com in 💟 💆 kdillmcfarland; https://kdillmcfarland.github.io/

Microbiology PhD with 10+ years experience applying data science and statistics to biological problems. Skilled leader of teams with diverse backgrounds and varied training. Expertise in next-generation sequencing from experimental design to publication. Effective communicator with formal teaching experience. Specific skills include:

| Data | Software | Statistics |
|---|--|--|
| Transcriptomics: RNA-seq, scRNA-seq Genetics: MegaEX, whole exome Epigenetics: ATAC-seq, bisulfite seq Proteomics: MS/MS Microbiome: 16S, 18S, ITS, meta- transcriptomics | AWS Git, GitHub R, Rmd, Shiny samtools, bedtools STAR, BWA, bowtie PLINK, vcftools mothur, QIIME | Linear, PLS, LASSO, latent regression Un/supervised machine learning PCA, NMDS, tSNE Sparse data imputation Data visualization |

EXPERIENCE

07/2021 - present

Senior bioinformatician, Allergy & Infectious Diseases, U. of Washington

- Lead a team of 4 bioinformaticians in the analysis of human 'omics data
- Director of the HIPC Data Management and Analysis Core at the Benaroya Research Institute
- Develop, standardize, and publish workflows in R packages, snakemake, and other software
- Contribute to grant writing and scientific publications
- Administrator of organizational GitHubs (36 users) and AWS (9 users)

07/2019 - 06/2021

Bioinformatician, Allergy & Infectious Diseases, U. of Washington

- Analyzed human transcriptomic, epigenetic, and genetic datasets including quality assessment and statistical tests
- Mentored researchers and students as Founder of the Bioinformatics Group at South Lake Union (BIGslu) and Informatics for TB (i4TB)

08/2017 - 06/2019 Post-doctoral research fellow, Microbiology & Immunology, U. of British Columbia

- Directed Experiential Data Science for Undergraduate Cross-disciplinary Education (EDUCE) including a team of 3 teaching assistants
- Designed and implemented data science curriculum in 7 courses
- **ECOSCOPE** fellow coordinating and teaching data science workshops for industry and academic partners

07/2016 - 06/2017 **Post-doctoral research associate**, Bacteriology/Sociology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Investigated relationships between the human gut microbiome and longterm behaviors in the Wisconsin Longitudinal Study (<u>WLS</u>)
- Navigated large, longitudinal survey databases

08/2011 - 06/2016 Graduate research assistant, Bacteriology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Designed and implemented amplicon sequence analysis pipelines
- Collaborated effectively with diverse international researchers resulting in first and corresponding author publications
- Mentored high school, undergraduate, and graduate students

EDUCATION

2011-2016 Ph.D. Microbiology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI. GPA: 4.00
 2007-2011 B.S. Molecular and cellular biology, Minor mathematics, U. of Puget Sound, Tacoma, WA. GPA: 3.84

RECENT PUBLICATIONS

Full publication list

Lindestam Arlehamn CS, Benson B, Kuan R, **Dill-McFarland KA** *et al.* 2022. T-cell deficiency and hyperinflammatory monocyte responses associate with MAC lung disease. preprint doi: 10.1101/2022.03.25.485768

Simmons JD, **Dill-McFarland KA** *et al.* 2022. Monocyte transcriptional responses to *Mycobacterium tuberculosis* associate with resistance to tuberculin skin test and interferon gamma release assay conversion. mSphere. In press. — <u>GitHub</u>

Dill-McFarland KA *et al.* 2022. Eosinophil-mediated suppression and Anti-IL-5 enhancement of plasmacytoid dendritic cell interferon responses in asthma. J Allergy Clin Immunol. Epub ahead of print. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2022.03.025 — GitHub

Dill-McFarland KA *et al.* 2021. An integrated, modular approach to data science education in microbiology. <u>PLoS Comput Biol</u> 17(2): e1008661. doi: <u>10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008661</u>

Dill-McFarland KA *et al.* 2019. Close social relationships correlate with human gut microbiota composition. <u>Sci Rep</u> 9: 703. doi: <u>10.1038/s41598-018-37298-9</u>

NOTABLE ACCOMPLISHMENTS

| 2017, 18, 19, 22 | Session convener American Society for Microbiology Microbe meeting |
|------------------|--|
| 2016 | Microbiome Digest's Best Microbiome Paper |
| 2016 | Sigrid Leirmo Memorial Award for peer mentorship and support |
| 2009, 2010 | American Society for Microbiology Undergraduate Research Fellow |

References available upon request